that the meeting is recording.
>> Hello, good afternoon everyone. Uh this
is Dominic Zerlo from the New Mexico
Department of Health and uh we do have a
few Department of Health staff members
who are here to assist. Um, but this is
the meeting for the end of life care
committee with the chair, uh, Larry
Leman. Um, and so we'll be turning it on
over to Larry here in just a moment. But
I just want to remind everyone that this
meeting is being recorded. We will post
recordings of all of our meetings. Um,
however, please remember it does take a
few days for those to go to become live
on our website. So, please allow for
about 5 to 10 business days. It's
usually much less, but please allow for
a few business days for that to happen.
Um, but we will have them available as
soon as possible. Several of the other
committee meetings and other meetings uh
are being posted here in the next day or
so. So, if you missed them and are
interested, you will be able to go back
and review them. And with that, I will
turn things on over to you. Uh, Dr.
Leman, it is your your meeting, sir.
>> Great. Thank you, Dominic. Thanks,
everybody. Good to see so many people
here. We're um we have 32 people here.
That's a impressive showing for our
first meeting which is which is awesome.
Um
my goal of the first meeting is is
twofold. One one is just to get to know
each other. You just to do some
introductions. The other is I was to
start to see if we can get a little bit
of a shared vision on what the committee
is um uh committee is doing. So, you
know, the way I've structured it so far
as to have us actually do, you know,
given the number of people we have, I'd
probably say like one to two minute uh
um introductions of yourself, what your
interest is, what's important to you,
and um then I'm going to drop us into um
looking at some bylaws and just looking
at some things that I think could be um
touchston for our our goals as a
committee. So, I'll share that after
we've each gotten to introduce
themselves. to introduce myself. I'm
Larry Leman. I'm um at the University of
New Mexico. Um I'm a professor of family
um obstetrics addiction medicine and do
research with psychedelic assisted
therapies and therapy and I'm delighted
to be on this committee.
How should we um how should we do it as
far as like a circle? Have you done in
other meetings as far as people uh
introducing themselves in some type of
an order? Any
>> uh yeah, if you would like, Larry, what
we can do is we can go down the list of
attendees and simply unmute them in
order and they can uh go ahead and
introduce themselves if that's how you
would like.
>> That sounds perfect.
>> Okay. So, uh, Adrian, I believe that you
were doing that is if you will unmute
individuals and call on them, uh, going
down the list.
>> Absolutely, Dominic. Thank you. So,
first off, we have Herk Rodriguez who
has his hand up. Herk, your mic has been
allowed. You will have to unmute it on
your end.
My name is Herk Rodriguez. I'm a small
business entrepreneur.
I'm interested in the uh end of life
care based on a business perspective.
I've uh got a couple of different
businesses now and we just opened up a
mushroom grow in downtown Albuquerque in
an old hundred-year-old adobe. Um, so
I'm open to any uh opportunity that is
available.
Fantastic. Thank you for that. We have
another question in the chat right now
with uh Lorine um who's asking, "Is
there a reason why we can't see one
another? Uh it is hard to know one
another without a visual." Dominic, do
you not?
>> Yeah, I actually was typing one in, but
I can speak it instead. Is part of the
reason is what we have discovered in
other large meetings, especially when
there's this many people, is that
individuals who are in rural or frontier
areas where there is not very good
internet, even if they stay off camera,
but other people are, they lose
connection regularly. We experience that
with some other meetings. And so, we
want to make sure that people can at
least participate. We do understand as
far as the visual uh that that sometimes
can be difficult but we would rather
have people participate rather than get
bumped off just simply due to uh
internet connection. So that is the
reason for it
>> and just to make it a little more simple
for all the members of the uh who are
attending today if you wish to introduce
yourself please pop your hand up and
when you do um our wonderful health
educator there Adrian will be able to
systematically uh unmute you and be able
and if again it won't be a case of you
being called out it's only if you feel
comfortable uh please pop your hand up
and and we can work it from it that way.
Thank you.
Thank you, Ishmael. Next, we have uh
Kate Hawk. Kate, your microphone has
been allowed. You will have to unmute
yourself.
>> Um, hey. Hawk, your credentials, your
microphone has been enabled. Go ahead
and speak.
>> Okay. Sorry, I I thought it was unmuted.
Now it is. Uh yeah, I'm Kate Hawk. I'm
in Santa Fe and I'm really happy to be
part of this. Love the process. It's
been so knowledgeable and respectful. So
I've been a trauma therapist for over 40
years. Um even before that I've been
working with psychedelics member of the
MAPS the multi-disiplinary association
for psychedelic studies since the 1980s
and I'm also uh working with
specifically death and expanded states
of consciousness including psychedelics.
I guess that's about all I will say
about myself right now except u happy to
be here and plan to participate fully in
this committee.
Thank you so much, Kate. Next, we have
up to speak is Danielle. Danielle, your
microphone has been enabled. Please
unmute yourself.
again. Danielle, your microphone has
been enabled. If you are on mute, please
unmute.
>> Okay. And Danielle stated in the I'm
sorry, Dominic, that she doesn't have
control of her mic or camera. Uh, so
Danielle, what we'll do is we'll go
ahead and um you can put that in the
chat if you like at least to still
engage. Um, also we have the email
posted if you're not comfortable posting
that in the chat as well. So that way we
may properly respond. So what I'm going
to do Danielle is go ahead and lower
your hand. And the next one in line to
speak is Asher. Asher, your microphone
has been enabled. Please unmute
yourself.
Hello, my name is Asher. Um, thank you
to this committee, everyone on the
board, and all the facilitators for this
group. Thank you. Um, yeah, I'm just
beginning my career as a hospice
chaplain, and I'm really interested in
learning about
um, how this is going to get phased into
hospice and um, yeah, just wanting to be
a part of the process. I'm really
excited about the potential for this um
to support people at the end of life and
to specifically to um offer that care
myself or create other uh pathways to
make that happen. Thank you.
>> Thank you very much for that. Danielle
in the chat has put that she is an end
of life guide and death doula with a
private practice conscious crossroads
end of life services. She also recently
founded the New Mexico death care
network a 5013 that helps provide end of
life care such as death doulas to those
who cannot afford it. Thank you for that
Danielle. If you'd like Danielle you can
raise your hand again and we will enable
your mic and we could try it again if uh
you have anything further to add. Next
in line uh to speak, I have Jen Catma.
Jen, your microphone has been enabled.
Please unmute yourself.
Hi. Uh my name is Jen Katma. Um I um
have a home in Truth of Consequences,
New Mexico. And I'm kind of um I'm at
the crossroads of a few different paths
uh into this space. One is um corporate
and public policy communications
um and also chapency and also
psychedelics. So um this is a really
interesting um place for me to spend
some time and learn and contribute as
much as I can. And I'm I'm really
interested in how we educate uh chaplain
to be also um providing kind of
spiritual counsel in a psychedelic
space. Um so that's a really keen
interest of mine. Um as well as
educating hospices and the roles they
can play. Um and and identifying those
hospices that are sort of raising their
hand. So nurturing them along the path
to become uh providers.
Thank you.
Thank you very much for that, Jen.
And as Dominic pointed out in the chat,
uh Dr. Rosen, just please verify that uh
you might have accidentally uh clicked
in multiple times. I know I just did
that. Um but if you're able to please uh
raise your hand again so that way we'll
definitely call on you. Next in line is
Katherine Waro. Katherine, your
microphone has been enabled. Please
unmute yourself.
Hello,
my name is Katherine Waro. I am a
licensed professional counselor in Los
Cusus, New Mexico. I have been working
with psychedelics
um for about 3 years now. Um I'm very
very excited especially about this
subcommittee because it's pushing the
envelope. uh the other states don't have
this um the end of life and I think that
this is going to be um a very exciting
and interesting um area. I'm here mostly
to provide any um I guess hands-on
expertise. I've been working with
clients um in this using psilocybin for
over three years. Um, I went to Therasil
in Canada to get trained and I also
offer training to practitioners doing
this work. Um, mostly because the
current offerings of training are
usually about $10,000 and a year long
and I wanted to be able to offer
something for people that mostly that
are already doing this work to offer
harm reduction. Um, I'm just here to
serve in any way possible and I'm very
grateful for everybody that's putting
their time and effort in this today.
Thank you.
>> Thank you for that, Katherine.
Next in line to speak is James Brown.
James, I've enabled your microphone.
Will you please unmute yourself?
>> Thank you. And, uh, good to see you, uh,
Dominic and Dr. Uh
my name is James Brown and I'm a doctor
of pharmacy here in New Mexico. Um I
have been trained in uh Oregon with the
use of psilocybin and solosin and uh my
background basically in end of life is
more palative style. I have over 13
years in the space of the current
western medicine. Um, I help current
hospicees with their their therapy
modalities
as well as uh treatments. Um, and I'm
very excited to be seeing New Mexico um
have access to this as one of those
treatment modalities um you know bring
it in as a medicine. I think this is
very important that we look at this and
and have access to this um for our
patients and I'm very excited to have
this opportunity to be part of this
wonderful group and there's some amazing
people here um and especially the chair
Dr. Leman I I really appreciate you uh
chairing this and everything that you've
done and so thank you sir and I'll keep
it simple um and I look forward to
everybody else talking to you in the
future. Thank you so much.
Thank you, James.
Next in line to speak is Meredith
McBranch. Meredith, your microphone has
been enabled. Will you please unmute
yourself?
>> Hi, my name is Meredith McBranch. Um,
I'm planning on going back to school in
clinical psychology and I'm really
interested in psychedelic assisted
therapies and I've watched several
family members move through the hospice
process. And so I think that you know
death and dying is a really important
part of life and ensuring equitable
access to psychedelic medicine no matter
where you are in the life process is
really important. So I wanted to be in
tune with what's happening in the state
as a future practitioner and just person
who lives here. So, thanks for um
creating the space.
>> Thank you, Meredith.
Next in line to speak is Brenda Burgard.
Brenda, your microphone has been
enabled. Will you please unmute
yourself?
>> Thank you. Um, my name is Brenda
Burgard. I am a licensed uh practitioner
here in the state of New Mexico. I am
also on the advisory board for training
and education
and um for psychedelics here and um I'm
also the president of decriminalization
of psychedelics of New Mexico and I um
I'm just here to hear maybe offer some
comments and to learn more about um what
we're doing in this committee here so um
I can add this to the training that We
need so just here in New Mexico. Thank
you very much.
>> Thank you, Brenda.
Next in line to speak is Lisa Ginsburg.
Lisa, your microphone has been enabled.
Will you please unmute yourself?
>> Hi everyone. Thank you for your time and
being here. Uh my name is Lisa. I'm
director of Chunga Institute. We provide
professional certification and so
facilitation in Oregon and Colorado and
uh having experience in Colorado
specifically as a state that allows uh
inh home treatments. I would
encourage to consider creating
additional training component and
requirement for end of life patients for
practitioners who want to work in end of
life care. um in addition to the
standard training for suicide
facilitation because these clients
require additional support and care.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Lisa.
Next up we have in line to speak is Dr.
Rosen. Dr. Rosen, your microphone has
been enabled. Will you please unmute
yourself?
Dr. Rosen, if you're speaking, we cannot
hear you. Your microphone is enabled.
Will you please unmute yourself?
All right. I'm sorry, Dr. Rosen. For
whatever reason, we still cannot hear
you. At this point, I'm gonna allow the
next person to uh go in line and see if
we can figure out what's going on. So,
next we have up in line is Aaron Ash.
Aaron, your microphone has been enabled.
Will you please unmute yourself?
Hi everyone. My name is Aaron Ash. I'm a
Albuquerque local. I consider myself a
little more part of the underground
psychedelic network for people who have
tried the western medicine route and
their experience kind of left them
either traumatized or institutionalized
and and just did not have the experience
that they wanted and so they sought um
different communities in order to
overcome um mostly a lot of uh addiction
work and uh from my time working in
addiction spaces I've noticed that
there's a a theme of people who can't
grieve. And so I've done some um variety
of different grief work and men's
retreats. And a key theme for me is uh
death and rebirth both at the individual
and collective level. So moving from old
self and old patterns into a new self
and new patterns. I really like the
Tibetan book of the dead quote um to die
before you die. And so I think it's
really important um just breathing
through the the fear of of death in
general seems to be a major theme. Um,
thank you.
>> Thank you, Erin.
Next in line to speak, I apologize in
advance if I don't pronounce it right.
Next is Jason Gentunin. Jason, your
microphone has been enabled. Will you
please unmute yourself?
>> Um, hi everyone. My name is Jason
Johnson. I'm a PMHNP student uh at the
University of New Mexico. Uh and I'm
just very grateful to be able to be part
of this forum. Um I have a very strong
interest in medical psilocybin therapy
and uh I'm just excited to learn more
about it. uh it's clinical applications
and uh any education or training
opportunities available to um clinicians
or future clinicians uh in that space.
So thank you.
>> Thank you Jason. Next in line to speak
is Dr. Lita Fatimi.
I'm sorry if I mispronounced that. Your
microphone has been enabled. Will you
please unmute yourself?
Yes, thank you so much for having me and
having this beautiful group of humans uh
doing great work. I'm Dr. Lita Fitmi. I
was an academic hospitalist at
University of New Mexico for a decade
and had a leadership position there too
and it's just so exciting that we are
moving forward with Salabin for end of
life. I'm now a founder of a hospice in
town, ABQ Hospice, and I'm very excited
to be able to offer this medicine for um
not only our patients uh who suffer at
the end of life, but also their
families. We also founded the um
conscious position psychedelics academy
which is the local academy and we have
CME providing through UN UNM school of
medicine which is I believe one of a
kind uh being able to to offer this and
nationally maybe there's maybe three
organizations uh that offer CME so we
really take pride in that and our class
just started and I just want to let you
all know that we are also holding
ourselves to the highest degree of
standard
following you, your lead of safety,
consent, of ethics, of integrity, and
making sure that um we're teaching that
to hospice providers in New Mexico. Um
so, yeah, thank you so much for leading
this uh Larry and this and Dominic and
everybody else who's here. Um it's we
are really leading the nation in this
work and your work is so important and
you're very much supported. Um thank you
so much.
>> Thank you Dr. Lita.
Next up to speak again apologies in
advance if for any misprononunciation.
James Hos. James your microphone has
been enabled. Will you please unmute
yourself?
>> Yes in perfect pronunciation. H so
uh thank you Dr. Leman uh for hosting
this meeting. Um good morning, good
afternoon everybody wherever you're at.
My name is James Hos and I'm a
pharmaceutical scientist based out of
Arizona and I'm currently collaborating
with the Arizona Department of Health
involved in psychoactive psychedelic
research. I'm deeply interested in this
committee particularly because it's a
very unique realm of endof life care and
I think that we need to prioritize
safety and be centered around patient
dignity in their time of need and I'm
really excited to learn from everybody
here today. Thank you.
Thank you very much, James.
Next up in line to speak, Dr. Rosen. Dr.
Rosen, your microphone has still been
enabled this whole time. Will you please
try to unmute yourself?
Dr. Razin, if you're there, we cannot
hear you. Unfortunately,
if we're having some sort of
connectivity issue, we've noticed if
people simply log out and close the
whole browser and Teams and log back in,
they'd be be more successful.
As of this time, Dr. Leman and Dominic,
I have no one with their hand raised to
speak and there's nothing in the chat as
of this moment.
I stand corrected. Next up to speak is
Van Warren.
Van, your microphone has been enabled.
Will you please unmute yourself?
Van, if you're speaking right now,
unfortunately, we cannot hear you. Your
microphone is enabled. Will you please
unmute yourself?
in the chat. Uh Van said he can't. And
Joanna put I'm sorry to be late, but I
was unable to join from my phone and I
finally arrived home. So glad to be
here. Thank you. Thank you for joining
us, Joanna. So at this point, Van, you
can put uh your correspondence if you
wish in the chat. If you're not
comfortable with that for whatever
reason, then you may email us. Next, I'm
going to go ahead and uh proceed to
Bareric Wolf. Eric, your microphone has
been enabled. Will you please unmute
yourself?
>> Eric, if you're speaking, unfortunately,
we cannot hear you. Can you please make
sure that your microphone is unmuted?
Unfortunately, Bareric, we cannot hear
you. If uh like I mentioned earlier,
usually if there's any type of technical
issue, you may need to log out and log
back in. In the chat, Dr. Rosen has
said, "I'm not sure why this isn't
working. I am a family physician in
Santa Fe, New Mexico. I'm an end of life
provider who offers medical aid and
dying as well as ketamine assisted
therapy at the end of life. specifically
for end of life anxiety. Very excited to
be here and very excited about the
prospect of adding psilocybin to our
menu of options for our patients in the
time of their need. And Laurian stated
maybe remind people where the microphone
icon is. Thank you, Laurian. We do have
a PowerPoint slide that's usually up
there.
And that slide is uh should be visible
at this time for individuals who are on
the computer. But just in case people
aren't able to see it for any reason, uh
the microphone icon is right next to the
camera icon in the upper right um of the
screen in the menu bar. If you are on
telephone, you just need to press star
six to unmute or mute.
>> Thank you, Dominic. Uh just for
clarification too, I'm not seeing
anything on mine except you and Lawrence
and whoever sharing their camera. Um
Van, thank you.
>> You I will try to
>> I don't know if that's working now.
>> There you are. Thank you, sir.
>> Okay, good. Um my name is Van Warren.
I'm a doctor of oriental medicine. I
live uh in the Albuquerque area. I um am
a death doula, end of life care
specialist.
I've worked as a chaplain and other
things in the realm of the spiritual
aspect of living and dying. And I want
to thank you for allowing me to be here
today and participate.
My um main concern
um and what I would like to bring to
this is a discussion about uh
accessibility. Who can who gets to use
these um this medicine for purposes of
end of life? And I'm sure that's what
we're going to be talking about a lot.
Um, but that's one of my big concerns
right now. And uh, thank you. I'm glad I
found the microphone icon.
>> Thank you for that, Ben.
>> All right. Next up to uh, speak is Beric
Wolf. Beric, your microphone credentials
have still been enabled from last time.
Will you go ahead and please try to
unmute by clicking on the microphone and
you may speak.
>> Uh, I think this is working now. Is that
right?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Okay, very good. Uh, again, Barack Wolf
um with End of Life Options New Mexico
and um we uh work on the sort of front
end of advanced care planning uh using
volunteers across the state uh who are
expert around those kinds of issues and
end of life options. Um and we also work
with the medical aid dying program uh
both in uh information uh working with
clinicians and hospices and um also
working with individual clients um who
express interest in medical aid and
dying. I love all the diversity of the
folks on the uh Zoom today or it's not a
Zoom. It's a I wish it were a Zoom. Uh
this is uh been hard to get used to this
uh platform and it's quirky. Um but uh
we'll figure it out. Uh Larry Leman,
thank you so much and I look forward to
learning a lot. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Eric.
Laurian offered feedback in the chat for
the PowerPoint slide to maybe uh it may
be helpful if stated if in the upper
right hand in the menu bar. Thank you,
Lauren.
And again, if anyone would wish to
speak, go ahead and please uh click on
the raise icon with the hand up.
and we will call on you accordingly.
All right. Next up to speak is Trina
Zer. Trina, your microphone credentials
have been enabled. Will you please
unmute yourself?
>> Hi everyone. My name is Trina Zaylor.
I'm a licensed clinical social worker
here in Albuquerque.
I have spent the past the majority of
the past 12 years doing particularly um
hospice and paliotative care at UNM in
the VA but I'm I'm here just
representing myself um joining these
things entirely on my own time. Um I'm
currently enrolled in the integrative
psychiatry institutees psych uh
psychedelic therapy training program. Um
they're uh through Boulder. That program
goes through the the end of February.
Very excited after being a a follower of
the work that Matt has been doing since
about 2004. Um been working on drug
policy at that time.
really excited to see these two
interests of mine converge um here in
New Mexico and to get a chance to
contribute to it and to help shape the
conversation that we have about using
this for you know what what I work with
every day um life anxiety and all that
anticipatory grief everyone
thank you Trina
next up to uh speak is Jennifer Johnson
your microphone credentials have been
enabled will you please unmute yourself?
>> Hello and thank you. Um I'm Jennifer
Johnson. I am an RN and I'm the clinical
director at Red Willow Hospice in
Talson, New Mexico. We have three
locations in um Albuquerque and Santa Fe
as well. And um we are um in process of
developing an end of life psychedelics
program. received a grant from um
Changing Minds Healing Hearts Foundation
um to develop this program. So, I'm
really excited um to be living in New
Mexico right now. I personally went
through the Nuropa psychedelics uh
facilitation certificate program in 2024
and now I'm getting to go through Dr.
Leita's program, the conscious
physicians program. So, um I love
getting to hear all of your voices and
this building of community and I cannot
wait to utilize these medicines um in
the end of life. I think it's going to
be really pivotal as it has been for my
own personal healing. So, thank you.
>> Thank you, Jennifer.
And again, as a friendly reminder, if
you wish to speak, please raise your
hand by hitting the raise hand icon. If
you're on a computer, it's the hand icon
at the top of the Teams window. If
you're on the actual app on your phone,
then you'll have to hit the three dots
for the menu and then the hand icon will
appear. Once we call on your name, uh
we'll enable your microphone so that way
you're able to unmute yourself and
speak.
If you're joining us through a telephone
today, it's star five to raise or lower
your hand.
>> Lawrence, are you able to hear me? Okay,
>> I am. I had to log in and out again. I
was also afflicted with the team's virus
apparently, but I'm back.
Perfect. Thank you for confirming.
>> Well, and it is great timing, Larry. Uh
it uh seems as though there are no other
individuals to introduce themselves at
this time. So, if you'd like, we can
move to the next item.
>> Yeah. Before I just want to shout out to
all of you, um you know, this is an
amazing group we have in the state here.
We have, you know, several hospice docs
interested, uh, you know, social
workers, death doulas, advocates, just
an amazing group that to be here. So,
I'm I just want to share my excitement.
Um, we're going to go into a little bit
of housekeeping here. I'm going to we're
going to have some bylaws and just deal
with a couple of little logistical
issues that have come up and then
hopefully we'll descend into the into
the interesting part here.
So, some bylaws that are really pretty
short here and, you know, sort of taken
off of some other ones here. Just want
to have people look at this with the
hope that we can uh approve these today.
Um,
>> we're known as a committee. Yes.
>> Before we go, I just want to make sure
people can see uh the document. Uh, if I
can get a few people to just do a thumbs
up or just say in the chat yes. Just
want to make sure that people can see
it. Okay. I'm seeing quite a few thumbs
up and thank you everybody. I appreciate
it. All right. Sorry, Larry. Go on
ahead.
>> No, that's great. So, um, a lot of this
is a sort of basic uh boiler plate sort
of thing. You know, the committee is the
committee, the board is the board. um
you know our focus is going to be on um
um safe uh patient safety, therapeutic
effectiveness, consistency, and then
there's a list of um of actual uh you
know scope and responsibility. I'm going
to cover that in a PowerPoint after
that, but I want to just go through the
rest of the bylaws before we do that. So
I'll cover those so we can scroll there.
Um wanted to mention a couple little
housekeeping on committee membership. um
you know committee members are basically
those who attend and participate in the
meeting. This is an inclusive group.
It's not an exclusive uh group uh
members include individuals with
expertise in these areas. Public members
strongly encouraged uh um especially
like people with chronic illness, cancer
survivors, those with lived experience.
Um one questions come up about
outofstate, you know, participants. And
here here's a an idea I'm proposing. You
know that outofstate participants
definitely can attend and definitely
speak at meetings, but they would not
have people count for the quorum or have
voting rights with the idea that this is
a a New Mexico program to New Mexicans.
I want to see if people have other
feelings on that, but we definitely want
to be inclusive, but I think it would be
an odd to have sort of a vote where we
had 10 people from out of the state out
voting. So that's my proposal.
Um the uh my responsibilities are
basically to convene the meetings and
talk about how often we have those and
be a liazison between the committee and
the board. Um we'll talk afterwards
about how often to to meet but I've had
suggestions of every two weeks or once a
month.
And um Kate has made a clarification
about how the word care is uh is is
there. Thank you Kate. I appreciate
that. Um I think that's an important
thing you know of the four indications
that are you know in the bill I think
it's important to remember that this is
not a disease end of life is a part of
the life process and a condition and
it's and it's care so that makes us
really different from the other
indications
um voting and recommendations a quorum
we're was going to say that um need to
have at least six members in either the
chair or representative again the out of
state participants may, you know, may
attend. Uh there's conflicts of
interest. Um it's important that people
disclose any actual or potential
conflicts of interest. Um and if you if
it's something that actually is
particular to your uh your interest, you
may need to uh excuse yourself from
voting.
So that's the the the bylaws. Before we
actually move to approve them, I'm
actually going to go back to that kind
of stuff in the middle here where we're
talking about the um the core areas here
that are um that are our scope of
practice. I think for ease of this, I'm
going to try something which I've never
been successful in doing, which is uh
sharing a PowerPoint uh on team. So,
wish me luck and I'm going to see if I
can do this.
Is that working?
>> Yes, I can can see it, Larry.
>> Yep.
>> Yes.
>> Great. Thank you. Thanks for your
patience. I'm fairly new to Teams
myself.
So, you know, as far as like the core of
what we're doing, um this was and this
is, you know, I developed, you know,
this but with with input from other
people in the community and um it
definitely uh you know, we'd love to
have thoughts of other things that are
important to be in our core role. But
the six that are written here is um you
know that we to define and discuss the
scope for end of life criteria,
therapeutic team development, inclusion
of family and caregivers, sites for end
of life care and education and workforce
development and finally an ongoing
review in the ME and updates. So those
are I'm going to go talk a little bit
about these six and then we'll open up
to a discussion about um those topics
and if there's other things that we
should be viewing as part of our
charter.
So um you know the definition scope for
end of life care you know again the
other the other indications are fairly
well defined depression substance use
here um end of life you know has more
variation I I see as part of our
committee to be able to look at um you
know to look at what is meant by end of
life care and consider that there could
be paliative care hospice care and
cultural perspectives um proposal that
we have an expansive time frames names
um including from the time of diagnosis
of serious turmoil or lifelimiting
medical conditions or from the time of
recognition that end of life is
approaching due to the natural um aging
process. Part of that is the whole idea
that the idea of the psychedelic
assisted therapy is to help people live
their life. It's not you know focused
just on helping people with uh with the
actual end of life.
Therapeutic team development um has come
up from a couple people already you know
and this this is the idea of developing
therapeutic care team models that extend
beyond a medical provider and licensed
therapist include you know paliative
hospital-based nurses social workers and
related professionals but also look at
emerging roles psychedelic end of life
doulas and I think we have a couple of
psychedelic chaplain on the call and
then one area to consider as we talk
about access and equity. It's come up a
discussion that the need for an
entrylevel facilitator role with
appropriate state lensure support for
inclusion in the program as part of the
care team. Um um you know working with
medical providers and licensed uh
licensed therapists. This comes from the
idea that unless we have, you know,
somebody that's at that entry level
role, it's going to be hard to run
things economically and pro promote
access
inclusion of family and caregivers. Um
this I think is novel you know likely to
the end of life you indication but look
at circumstances under which life
partners family members or caregivers
may participate in psilocybin assisted
therapy is part of end of life care um
and that that may seem like a novel you
know idea but the way I would view that
is um this is about end of life care and
it doesn't mean that the only person
who's the person who's having end of
life can uh participate this may be very
helpful um for the partners and
caregivers to be able to have the
opportunity to participate.
Where should end of life care hap
happen? I think that's an important area
for us to um uh discuss. You know, we've
heard several people here mention home.
You know, I know as the bill that
developed, you would always mention that
um end of life care in particular may be
important to, you know, support
homebased care and coordinating with
hospicees, home health care agencies and
healthcare and therapy facilities.
Education and workforce development. I
was happy to hear several people brought
that up already. Supporting educational
workforce development related to
psilocybin assisted therapy. And I think
this will be important you know to be
interfacing with the you know the
committees that are working on the areas
of education working on workforce um uh
you know development.
I think that there, you know, the idea
that that all everyone who's trained for
using psilocybin assisted therapy has
some exposure to um end of life care uh
but also make sure that we have the
availability of of trainings that are
going on you nationally for people that
are interested in being um having a more
in-depth role of end of life psychedelic
care.
And then ongoing review and development
maintain a process of periodic review of
uh emerging scientific literature,
clinical guidance and program data. You
know, there's um besides the other state
programs here, you know, there's people
up in Canada that are using psilocybin
friend of life care. There's Arizona,
there's a real interest in uh um the
ability to use psilocybin um under um
the right to try legislation. And so I
think it'll be important for us to stay
up on all of those. So anyway, that
that's that's just an overview of of six
areas, but I' I'd like to throw open to
discussion here about, you know, both
what do people think about um you know,
these six areas as being important? Are
there major other things that we're that
we're missing? And and certainly this is
not a this is an ongoing process and and
we can be revising things but you know
just at the beginning to to open up that
discussion.
>> Dr. Lita is uh first Dr. Lita your
microphone credentials have been
enabled. Go ahead and unmute yourself.
>> Thank you so much and thank you for the
for the list of things Larry. I think
one of the questions that I have as a
hospice physician is the criteria that
determine an individual has the end of
life uh diagnosis.
Is it something that the diagnosis is by
CMS criteria? because that's what we use
currently in the hospice world is
eligibility of hospice criteria that is
set forth by CMS guidelines um which
tend to be robust but at the same time
for example in a patient who's been
given the diagnosis of dementia if
they're hos hospice appropriate they are
no longer able to their fast score is 7D
which you know as physicians we know
that's you know they're pretty much
non-verbal
they can't consent, they can't, you
know, do any of that which doesn't deem
them appropriate for psilocybin therapy.
Um, and so my question would be is is
our definition would be are we catching
these patients at the beginning of the
diagnosis where um they've been just
diagnosed with
mild dementia for example. I think those
types of things we need to be aware of
because the CMS policies and eligibility
criteria is pretty advanced disease. Um
just a thought.
Thank you. Next up to speak is Trina.
Trina, your microphone credentials have
been enabled. Will you please unmute
yourself?
>> I have two comments. One to piggyback on
what uh Dr. Patenny was just stating. Um
my my hope is that
uh we'll be able to offer this program
for for people who perhaps do have a
diagnosis but are far before reaching a
a hospice qualification. And um was
having the bulk of my experience
prior to about two years ago being
predominantly in paliotative care and
seeing
this really potent window for helping
people to um wrestle with their
existential distress and to
build relationships with themselves and
with and with family while they still
have the the health and wellbeing to be
able to do it. I think that would be a
really important um program that we
could offer. And then secondly, forgive
me if this was in the slides, but I
wonder if we also want to add um in your
discussion about the role of of
integration and mostly it comes up to me
in thinking about the equity fund and
for people accessing this therapy. if we
have also
some type of parameters that that we
discuss about having that integration
support following the the medicine. Um
maybe that will also open up funding
sources for people who you know perhaps
have um Medicare plans that are that are
really um restrictive on you know
providing behavioral health um support
or other limitations.
Thank you.
Next up is Denali Wilson.
Denali, your microphone credentials have
been enabled. Will you please unmute
yourself?
>> Hey. Um, hi everybody. Um,
thank you. I'm grateful to be here. I am
really excited about a number of things
that you've laid out here, Dr. Leman. I
want to especially um express express
gratitude and excitement for um the
early recognition that there needs to be
um there needs to be an entrylevel
facilitator role that is permitted and
authorized within the program. I I'm
really curious because I think we have
to work within the language of SB219
which I don't think precludes that but
does require some thoughtful thinking
about whether you know the department
itself can create its own certification
program as has been done in other
spaces. it may be helpful to have a um
an early conversation with this
committee um and and others potentially
the the legal department at the
department of health about what would be
needed to make that viable. I think it's
not only really important for
affordability and accessibility in this
care protocol around end of life but for
all of the different indications. It's
going to be really important that we
find a way to make that happen.
Thank you.
Okay, then your microphone credentials
have been enabled. Will you go ahead and
please unmute yourself?
>> Yes, thank you. Um,
it struck me as wonderful when I read
what you put up there about family
members. Uh because as anyone who's been
around
um someone dying, yes, it's happening to
that person, but the whole family is
involved if the family is involved. Um
which sometimes is not the case. But uh
and of course that brings up the
question of um if we involve family
members in the actual uh use of the uh
psilocybin
uh they do not have a diagnosis of uh
imminent death. Although as we all know
we're all going to die. So we do all
have that diagnosis. It's just not
necessarily seen as imminent. Um so how
that gets worked around in the law to uh
have availability for family members and
others uh who are in on this dying
process u is extremely important and I
thank you for including that and somehow
hopefully it'll get all worked out.
>> Thank you.
All right, next up is Danielle.
Danielle, your microphone credentials
have been enabled. Will you please
unmute yourself?
>> My mic is working now. Fantastic. Um,
>> yeah, along with Van's comment, I'm
curious about how we can make it work,
but also the idea of extending the
timeline for which family members have
access, meaning for after the death has
occurred for bereiement and grief
support. Um,
you know, at the way codes work and
diagnoses and everything, can we do that
without it being complicated grief just
for everyday run-of-the-mill grief, if
you will? Um, so yeah, I think that's
something that I'm really curious about
the family support.
>> Thank you.
>> Again, as a friendly reminder, if anyone
wishes to speak, if you're on a
computer, please click on the hand icon
near the top of the Teams window. It
says raise under the icon. If you're on
the actual Microsoft Teams app on your
phone, you'll need to press the three
dots, which will give you access to the
menu for the hand icon to appear and
select it. And if you're joining us
through a phone, it's star five to raise
or lower your hand.
Okay, Larry, we're not seeing anyone
else with raising their hand. So, uh,
except for you. So, it's back to you,
Larry.
>> Thanks, Tom. Appreciate that. Um, this
is good. I mean, it sounds like we have
a lot of support and consensus around a
lot of the uh a lot of the issues that
we want to talk here. I I would I picked
up one issue that does seem to be worth
um uh adding to the six on there which
is basically what is the therapeutic uh
care plan for end of life regarding
integration number of sessions. And so
if people are in agreement, I can add
that as a a seventh item to the uh to
the scope of responsibilities
and we'll we'll come up with a good name
for it. But but basically for a
placeholder can be uh um uh development
of optimal um therapeutic uh plans of
care for end of life.
And uh it looks like
uh I'm sorry, Katherine,
your microphone has been enabled. If you
wish to say something, please unmute
yourself.
>> Yeah, I just wanted to say, but I think
Larry, you did cover it that I wanted to
make sure that prep was also included,
not just integration. And I think your
new wording included that. So, thank
you.
>> Thanks, Katherine.
Next up is Dan. I apologize in advance
if I mispronounced your last name. Dan
Husen. Dan, your microphone credentials
have been enabled. Will you please
unmute yourself?
>> Hi. Um, sorry I'm a little bit late to
this meeting. Um, I just wanted to try
to be a part of every one of them and
let you guys all know that I can be a
resource. Um, my name is Dan. I'm with
Rose City Laboratories in Portland,
Oregon. We do uh the licensed psilocybin
testing. We have been for the last three
years since we program has been in
operations.
I've seen a lot of uh fluxes and changes
in the industry and the way things are
going. Um so unfortunately I missed a
lot of this conversation with you guys
but um I am a resource. I can uh I've
done a we've done a lot of studies when
it comes to psilocybin
mushrooms and um different effects when
it's mixed with different things and
versus boiling versus non- boiling and
different studies on psilocybin that
could be beneficial and helpful. Um we
found that if you don't boil when you
make tea that things are not um things
degrade really rapidly and are not
locked in versus boiling. So, if it's
okay with you guys, I can drop that in
the chat. Um,
I just really encourage uh meet the meet
the people where they're at and um try
to not um h have to make them go
somewhere to do something. Um the end of
life people um I can understand for
sport people and everybody else, but end
of life people, try to meet them where
they're at. Thank you.
Thank you.
>> Larry, there's no one else with their
hands up at this time. So, back to you.
>> Great. You know, I I I think there's a
theme in a couple of different issues. I
want to share my my thoughts on this,
which is well, what can we do? I mean,
you know, what is the law? What can we
do? And I I would encourage us as a
committee to uh start out thinking what
we think is the best thing. What is the
the best thing for New Mexico in the
state? And then yes, we'll have to get
some, you know, legal opinions on
different things. My my own opinion from
reading the bill is that um it doesn't
specify an indication of let's say
anxiety or depression associated with
end of life. It's end of life care. And
so end of life care would be covered by
you know for a partner caregiver but
again I'm the physician not the lawyer
but that would be my interpretation of
that. Um I think similarly as far as you
know the role of the you know developing
facilitator different things you know I
I would encourage us to take our best
you know shot at what what's the vision
of ideal care and then sort through you
know how does that work out as far as
the uh needing to create another
position. I really appreciate Denali
bringing up the, you know, that that
question because I I have heard that
there there may need to be another bill
or such um to add a facilitator
position. I've also heard other people
saying perhaps not, but perhaps the DO
can create that. But I think our our
goal early on could be to develop the
best program um that we we can envision.
Anyone
want to move to approve the minutes of
the uh bylaws?
>> Or maybe more importantly, anyone
opposed to approving the bylaws?
>> Yeah. And I was just going to say,
Larry, uh since this is a more of a
working group, all you really need is
sort of a consensus with regard to that.
And so I would recommend just if anybody
has an objection to the bylaws uh with
the uh the portion of Dr. Leman adding
in that last section regarding the
development of optimal care plans. Um uh
that go ahead and raise your hand at
this time and otherwise we'll move
forward with them as adopted if that's
okay with you. Larry
>> sounds good to me. I'm not seeing
anybody raise their hand. We'll give it
just a few moments more.
>> All right, Larry, you have bylaws for
your committee.
>> So,
>> excellent. Thank you.
>> I guess the next topic to me is how do
we move forward? Like what's the what's
our best way to move forward? One of
those would be the question of how often
should this group meet? Um um you know,
just just speaking to people, I've heard
people suggest every once a month, every
two weeks. Um I'm going to just propose
myself that we start out with every two
weeks and and see where that goes. We
may decide that that's too often, but it
hopefully it'll get us off to a quick
start. So, I wanted to see what people
think about that. Thumbs up, thumbs
down. You How do you
want to be? There's nothing preventing
us from meeting more often, but I think
getting more than every two weeks tends
to be hard for most people's schedules.
I want to call mention this. Uh Senator
Senator Jeff has um as a bill sponsor
shares the opinion as far as uh the wide
wide view about uh rules. So we thank
you very much Dr. Steinberg.
>> Gentlemen, we have Dr. Roxroy Reed uh
raising their hand to speak. Dr. Dr.
Roxray, your microphone credentials have
been enabled. Will you please unmute
yourself?
Dr. Reed, if you're speaking,
unfortunately, we cannot hear you. As a
friendly reminder, please make sure you
tap on the microphone icon if you're on
Teams on the computer or on the app. If
you are on a phone, I believe it is star
six to unmute.
Dr. Reed, unfortunately, again, we
cannot hear you. So, if you don't mind
sharing your correspondence in the chat,
we will also provide the email to you uh
if you wish to do that.
Okay. And Larry, we do have several
people who have commented in uh the chat
that two weeks is good. So, I would say
similar to the bylaws, if there's no
objections, we just move forward with
two weeks. That would put the next
meeting at Thursday, January 22nd at 300
p.m.
>> Sounds good. Okay, not seeing anybody
with objecting on that and Larry giving
us a thumbs up. Um, we'll go ahead and
the department will get that scheduled.
Um just as a a logistical note for
individuals, one of the things that we
are doing uh is as we get those meetings
scheduled, we are sending out a weekly
uh or or almost weekly because we're
waiting for these first several meetings
of the different committees to conclude
so that we can actually then post in one
email and send it out through the
constant contact which is our email list
and send it out with a list of all of
the links and the different committee
meetings and times.
So, we should have that. We do have a
couple of more meetings over the next
couple of business days and then about
the middle of next week, we should be
sending out that notification with all
the new meeting updates and links. So,
just to let everybody know uh from a
logistic standpoint. So, just bear with
us for a couple more business days until
the last of the initial meetings have
passed and we'll get them all out again
in one email. And if you have not signed
up for the constant contact, um the way
to do that is actually go to the New
Mexico Department of Health website
www.nmhealth.org
and in the upper right hand side there's
a little link saying sign up for e-news
and uh once you click on that link it'll
take you to an information sign up page.
You just sign up include your
information, email uh and then click on
the medical psilocybin program box. You
can also by the way if you have interest
in some of the other topics click on
those boxes as well. You can click
multiple boxes at the same time and then
just click sign up. Uh you may then need
to confirm that as usual you are not a
robot. Um and then once you do that
you'll be added to our constant contact
email list and be able to receive
updates and notifications about the
program. And we are sending out all of
the um the uh the meeting links as we do
have the next meeting set up. We're
sending them through there so you can be
assured that you won't miss them. The
one thing of course is as with any email
list, please always check your junk mail
folder. Sometimes uh email list items do
go to junk mail. So uh we just want to
make sure that people who would like to
get information are able to do so. Um,
and then again, just as a reminder, when
the meeting is over, if you were not
able to speak for any reason or you
think of something that you would like
to include in as part of public comment,
um, and did not do so during the
meeting, if you send it to our email at
medical.silicybin.nm.gov,
which is also in the chat, we will
include it in the meeting record. for it
to be included for this meeting. Please
send it by the end of day tomorrow,
January 9th, at 5:00 PM. And now I'm
going to go back to you, Larry. Uh I
think I've gone through enough of the
logistics at the moment.
>> Thanks as always, Dom. Um I wanted to
just propose a structure at least for
the for the first few meetings. um you
know we have um really sort of a
relatively distinct field here of end of
life psilocybin care and we have a lot
of resources both here and out of state
I'm going to propose that we include
maybe a 15 to 20 minute educational
presentation by people in different
areas at each of the meetings for
instance we might have a end of life
chaplain so we can learn about that we
might have um you know people who've had
experience offering end of life uh uh
care in different ways is and as a way
of sort of doing self-education that may
eventually include like clarifications
on some you know legal issues or other
issues but just as a way of doing
self-education
and the the other part of that would be
we we now have like seven areas so that
people could start um we'll have to
figure out how to coordinate that at the
meetings but think a little bit about
which of those areas are of particular
interest like maybe you know you're
really interested in the therapeutic
care plan. So, you know, this is a
subcommittee, but we can have a smaller
group in that in that that meets and and
talks like outside of these meetings and
then presents it to us. So, I'd like to
encourage people that, you know, the
goal of this to be kind of an
interactive co-creating. So, think think
going towards the next meeting um are
there areas that you're particularly
interested in? And um I dropped my email
there. That's my work email. It's um I'm
happy to get uh get emails if people
have thoughts about who might be good to
come speak with us or conversely just
like I want to learn about this and then
make it my job to find somebody. But
either way and we'll um you know try to
get get that keep it interesting and
educate each other. But that these are
just my ideas of doing this. I also want
to see if people have other thoughts.
I'm propos right now we have a Q2 week
meeting proposing having some education
you know groups coming together any
other thoughts on the way to move
forward as a committee
>> if you have other thoughts raise your
hand put it in the chat or if you just
like what I'm saying thumbs up or you
know
>> thank you Lord Next up or ne first
requesting to speak is James Basabi.
James, your microphone credentials have
been enabled. Will you please unmute
yourself?
>> Yes. Thank you. Uh Dr. Leman, I
absolutely love the fact that you want
to bring on individuals to shed light on
their expertise. Just yesterday, we had
a Senate meeting um of the right to try
here in Arizona and really pushed that
through Dr. Sue Sisley. So, I think it's
an excellent uh route to explore and um
I'd love to um maybe make that warm
introduction to get people on from
Arizona to help with New Mexico. Thank
you.
>> Thank you. I'm just going to share share
something. Um Sue is actually has some
connection to New Mexico at UNM. We're
going to be doing um psilocybin research
in alignment with the state program. Uh
Sue is the uh the only FDA approved
grower of psilocybin mushrooms and her
psilocybin infused chocolates will be
used in our research from Scottsdale,
Arizona.
>> Thank you for clarifying, Dr. Leman.
Next up requesting to speak is James
Brown. James, your microphone
credentials have been enabled. Will you
please unmute yourself?
Hey Larry, I was uh hoping that we'd
kind of focus on because of this elderly
population typically that we're looking
at, you know, the pharmaccoinetics and
dynamics is very very unique and
psilocybin, you know, works in those
people population differently than
typically that we'll see in these other
groups that'll be, you know, potentially
using this medicine. Um and I just want
to make sure that the group focuses on
that as well as like you know besides
the age and um everything from weight to
their renal function I mean their liver
functions because of the P450 enzymes
you know medications is a big thing with
the elderly we're on a lot of polyarm
pharmacy um and then this might interact
with some of those polyfarm pharmacy
things and so I like to see the group
kind of focus on some type of I don't
know screening or some type of tools
tools um necessary that we can use for
practitioners uh so they feel
comfortable and educated.
Thank you, James.
Next up, requesting to speak is Dr.
Reed. Dr. Reed, your microphone
credentials have still been enabled from
your last request. Will you please
attempt to unmute yourself?
Dr. Reed, unfortunately, if you're
speaking, we cannot hear you. As a
friendly reminder, if you are on the
Microsoft Teams application on your
computer, there will be a microphone
icon uh usually towards the top right, I
believe. Uh otherwise, you can go to the
directly to the icon if you're in the
Teams app. And if you're joining us by
telephone, it's star six to mute or
unmute.
I apologize. But again, Dr. Reed, we
cannot hear you. If you wish to maybe
possibly log out and log back in or you
can put your correspondence in the chat
and Dominic has made the email available
if you would prefer that method as well.
Okay. And Larry, there's no one else in
the chat as far as for speaking, so back
to you.
Well, what I would say is if um if we
don't have any more uh comments or
suggestions, then we um we get to call
it a little bit early. Get get a half
hour of your life back and we'll we'll
wind up here. I think what we'll do is
continue to schedule the meetings at two
hours. But personally, I think two hours
is a long meeting and I think if we wind
up winding up at, you know, an hour and
a half or hour and 15 minutes, that's
just great. But if we we'll make it in a
two-hour slot so we have the ability to
to be expansive. Um um my email is there
if there's thoughts of thoughts of um
topic speakers. Um um I I appreciate we
already got four or five good topics
that we want to learn about here. So
we'll move ahead on some of those and
and uh I will present all of our our
good thoughts at the board meeting next
week. So thanks everybody and enjoy your
week.
>> Thank you everybody on behalf of the
department and thank you Dr. Leman for
uh hosting and sharing the meeting and
everybody for joining and thank you to
Senator Jeff Steinborn for joining in
and listening in. So uh thank you
everybody. Have a great uh rest of your
day. And for those who are interested in
being on any of the other meetings, you
can find them in our website in the
announcement sections. We do have them
there uh with the links available. Uh
and tomorrow's meetings are uh the uh
the research and improvement committee
and the propagation committee. So thank
you everyone.